Rhiannon: The emotional health
of children and young people is
increasingly recognised as being
fundamental to their wellbeing.
As emotional health is nurtured
primarily in the home, as long as this
is a calm and loving environment, it
can only be positive for the future
prospects of individuals and communities.
Leah: The good emotional health of
children and young people is vital to
them as individuals, as being emotionally
healthy is an important end in itself
and is also linked with a range of
positive outcomes in later life.
It does not necessarily mean being
happy all the time, but it does
mean having the resilience to face
the challenges that occur in life.
Rhiannon: The good emotional health
and well-being of children and young
people is also vital to society, as
poor mental health in children and
young people is associated with teenage
pregnancy, bullying, violent and
criminal behaviour and substance misuse.
The majority of adults with mental
health problems experienced mental
health concerns in childhood.
These problems not only persist
through to adulthood but can also
have an impact the next generation.
Leah: The development of emotional health
starts even before a child is born,
with the first two years of life being
critical for putting in the foundations
for emotional health throughout childhood.
This then follows onward into adult life,
through the parent to child relationship.
Promoting the emotional health of
children and young people can be
done by supporting friendships, peer
relationships and personal development,
within early years, school and college
settings and by providing additional
advice and support if problems arise.
Rhiannon: Conduct disorders can be
difficult to diagnose, as some of
these troublesome behaviours can be
a result of environmental factors
or other mental health conditions.
Leah: A child who has a poor emotional
environment with poor role models
may struggle to develop positive
relationships with their peers.
They may fall behind academically and risk
later involvement in risky behaviours.
They may also develop physical and mental
health issues in their adult life and are
unlikely to reach their full potential.
A good emotional environment will
provide a secure base for children
to grow into well-rounded resilient
adults with good mental health.
A child’s social and emotional development
is vital for their future, if they are
to achieve their full potential socially,
academically and career-wise as an adult.
Strong bonds with a parent or carer
can help to develop a resilience to
stress, an ability to balance emotions
and enable the child to have meaningful
interpersonal relationships in the future.